Guide to the Arthur Sperry Pearse papers, 1904-1960 UA.29.02.0012
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Arthur Sperry Pearse papers
1904-1960
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Pearse, A. S. (Arthur Sperry), 1877-1956
UA.29.02.0012
18 Linear Feet 16 boxes
Arthur Sperry Pearse (pronounced like "purse") was Professor of Zoology at Duke University from 1927 until his retirement in 1948. Collection primarily contains papers and other items relating to his academic career: correspondence, writings and lectures, lab notes and data, fieldwork notes, teaching materials, clippings and printed materials, many photographs and negatives, and glass slides. Images are of animal and plant life, but also include landscapes, people, villages, and social customs from about 1915-1935 in Nigeria and the Yucatán Peninsula, and smaller groups from other research trip locations in South America and Southeast Asia, 1910s-1930s. There are also early photographs and materials regarding the Marine Biology Laboratory in Beaufort, N.C. and other marine labs, as well as images of the Outer Banks coast and people such as fishermen. A large group of images consist of illustrations used in Pearse's textbooks, articles, and teaching lectures. Prominent subjects throughout the collection include the establishment of and research projects at the Duke University Marine Laboratory, the promotion of forestry as a scientific discipline at Duke, Pearse's role as editor of the publication Ecological Monographs, and his research interests: marine biology, ecology, crustaceans, parasitology and parasitic diseases, microbiology and biological adaptation, and forestry.
Access Restrictions
Access partially restricted: negatives are closed to use. Some images are available in the form of prints.
Provenance
The Arthur Sperry Pearse Papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer between 1954-1973.
Biographical Note
Arthur Sperry Pearse (pronounced like "purse") was born 15 March 1877, on the Pawnee Indian Reservation near Crete, Nebraska, where his parents ran a trading post. In 1898, Pearse left the University of Nebraska with the 4th Nebraska Volunteer Infantry in the Spanish-American War, returning to receive his B.A. in 1900 and his M.A. in 1904. He went on to complete his doctoral work at Harvard where he received his Ph.D. in 1908. Also, in 1942, Pearse received an honorary LL.D. from the University of Nebraska.
Pearse taught courses at Harvard, the University of Michigan (1908-1910), the University of the Philippines (1911), St. Louis University School of Medicine (1911-1912), the University of Wisconsin-Madison (1912-1927), and, finally, as Professor of Zoology at Duke University (1927-1948). In 1926, Pearse spent five months at the London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine and one year as a visiting professor at Keio University in Japan (1929-1930). Pearse was an instrumental participant in the creation of the Duke University Marine Laboratory at Beaufort, N.C., in 1938 and served as the lab's first director until 1945. He was also founder and editor of Ecological Monographs (1930-1950), a publication of Duke University Press.
In addition to work within the academy, Pearse was also a special investigator for the United States Bureau of Fisheries, a special member of field staff for the International Health Board, and a special investigator for the Carnegie Institute. Also a member of many scientific societies, he served as president of the Ecology Society of America (1925), American Society of Zoologists (1945), and North Carolina Academy of Science (1951), and as vice president of the American Association for the Advancement of Science (1936).
During his career Pearse authored about 175 publications on a variety of research interests in the fields of marine zoology and ecology, microbiology, forestry, and parisitology including fresh-water fauna, beach and estuarine animals, the fauna of soil and forest environments, parasitic marine crustacea, and biological adaptation. Titles include General Zoology (1917), The Migration of Animals from Sea to Land (1936), Fauna of the Caves of the Yucatan (1938), and Animal Ecology (1939). He also published a collection of essays, Hell's Bells (1941), and an autobiography, Adventure: Trying to be a Zoologist (1952).
Pearse's research travels - documented by his own photographs - took him to the Nigeria, the Philippines, Japan, Yucatan, Venezuela and numerous locations throughout the United States including Alabama, Wisconsin, Massachusetts, Maine, Florida, Texas, and coastal North Carolina.
Collection Overview
The Arthur Sperry Pearse papers include the professional papers and photographs of A. S. Pearse's scholarly career. His professional papers span the length of his academic career and include: correspondence, writings and lectures, lab notes and data, fieldwork notes, teaching materials, clippings and printed materials, many photographs and negatives, book illustrations, and glass slides. Images are of animal and plant life, but also landscapes, people, villages, and social aspects of life from about 1915-1935 in Nigeria and the Yucatán Peninsula, and from other research trip locations in South America and Southeast Asia, 1910s-1930s. Included are snapshots of fellow scientists in the laboratory and in the field. There are also early photographs and materials regarding the Marine Biology Laboratory in Beaufort, N.C. and other marine labs, as well as images of the N.C. coast and people such as fishermen. A large group of images consists of illustrations used in Pearse's textbooks, articles, and teaching lectures.
Prominent subjects throughout the collection include the establishment of and research projects at the Duke University Marine Laboratory, the promotion of forestry as a scientific discipline at Duke, Pearse's role as editor of the journal Ecological Monographs, and his research interests: marine biology, ecology, crustaceans, parasitology and parasitic diseases, microbiology and biological adaptation, and forestry.
Correspondence primarily reflects his role as editor of Ecological Monographs which includes correspondence concerning receipt of drafts for publication, recommended revisions, and future publication dates. Other prominent topics include Pearse's involvement with professional organizations, various symposiums and conferences, publications, research in Nigeria and the Yucatán, and the founding and early operations of the Duke University Marine Laboratory at Beaufort, North Carolina. Also, in 1938-1939, there is a series of correspondence between Pearse and President William Preston Few concerning lack of support for and conditions within the department and Pearse's consequent resignation as departmental chair.
Other materials include research notes, tables, and sketches; graduate student correspondence, plans of work, and dissertation abstracts; manuscripts of various publications authored by Pearse including Animal Ecology and his 1952 autobiography, Adventure: Trying to be an Ecologist; laboratory and field notebooks containing research notes and statistics from Nigeria, the Yucatan, Wisconsin, and various other research locations.
There are many photographic prints, nitrate and safety negatives, and glass-plate lecture slides, all documenting Pearse's research travels, particularly in Nigeria and the Yucatán, but also in Alabama, Florida, and coastal North Carolina, Japan, China, Burma, the Phillippines, Colombia, and Venezuela. Images include local flora, fauna, landscapes, villages, localized crafts and industries, and indigenous peoples, as well as maps, charts, tables, drawings, and photographs used in Pearse's lectures and publications.
Related Material
Irving Emery Gray Papers, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Marine Laboratory Records, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Paul Jackson Kramer Papers, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
University Archives Photograph Collection, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
William Preston Few Records and Papers, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Conditions Governing Access
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Adaptation, Biological; Biology -- Fieldwork; Coastal biology; Ecology -- Study and teaching (Higher); Forest ecology; Marine biology; Marine ecology; Parasitic diseases; Parasitic diseases -- Nigeria; Zoology -- North Carolina; Zoology -- Study and teaching (Higher); Beaufort (N.C.) -- History; Nigeria -- Photographs; Nigeria -- Social life and customs; North Carolina -- Outer Banks -- Photographs; Yucatán (Mexico: State) -- Social life and customs; Yucatan Peninsula -- Photographs; Black-and-white negatives; Black-and-white photographs; Cellulose nitrate film; Field notes; Lantern slides; Negatives (photographs); Slides (photographs); Few, W. P. (William Preston), 1867-1940; Pearse, A. S. (Arthur Sperry), 1877-1956; Duke University. Department of Zoology; Duke University. Marine Laboratory; Duke University. School of Forestry; American Association for the Advancement of Science; American Society of Zoologists
- Correspondence, 1921-1960; 1.5 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence primarily reflects his role as editor of Ecological Monographs, and relates to drafts for publication, recommended revisions, and dates for future publication. Other prominent topics include Pearse's involvement with professional organizations, including the Ecology Society of America and Society of American Zoologists; various symposiums and conferences, publications, and research; and the founding and early operations of the Duke Marine Biology Laboratory at Beaufort, North Carolina.
  Correspondence also reflects Pearse's professional activities outside of the academy: working for the Office of the Quartermaster General interviewing soldiers recently returned from tropical environments in New Guinea, India, Burma, and the Caribbean; promoting the physical rehabilitation of the sciences in Europe in the wake of the Second World War through the American Association for the Advancement of Science; and acting as special investigator for the U.S. Bureau of Fisheries, the International Health Board, and the Carnegie Institute.
  In 1938-1939, there is a series of correspondence between Pearse and Duke University President William Preston Few concerning conditions within and lack of support for the Department of Zoology and Pearse's consequent resignation as departmental chair. Series is arranged chronologically.
  - 1921-1944, 15 folders (Box 1)
  - 1945-1960, undated, 10 folders (Box 2)
- Subject Files, 1914-1958 and undated; 2 boxes
  The bulk of the subject files reflect Pearse's research interests and his involvement with professional organizations and institutes. Materials include correspondence, memoranda, reports, and hand-written notes. Prominent subjects include research and staffing at the Beaufort Marine Lab, his work for Ecological Monographs, his 1926 tenure at the London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine, the National Science Foundation, and numeruous zoological and ecological research topics.
  - Anemotropism, Rheatropism, Geotropism, undated (Box 2)
  - Animal behavior:
    - 1928-1929 (Box 2)
    - 1931-1938 (Box 2)
  - Beaufort, plan for resident investigator, undated (Box 2)
  - Beaufort research, 1932-1941 (Box 2)
  - Bibliographies, undated (Box 2)
  - Bimini, 1948-1949 (Box 2)
  - Biological data handbook, 1948-1949 (Box 2)
  - Carnegie Institute of Washington, 1928-1933 (Box 2)
  - Chemical senses, 1934, undated (Box 2)
  - Cockroaches, 1937-1938 (Box 2)
  - Color, 1936-1937, undated (Box 2)
  - Duke University committees, undated (Box 2)
  - Ecological Monographs abstracts, 1930-1948 (Box 2)
  - Ecological Monographs, 1931-1951 (Box 2)
  - Eustylochus, undated (Box 2)
  - Fish anatomy, undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Fishes, undated (Box 2)
  - Forest identifications, 1942-1943 (Box 2)
  - Hell's Bells, undated (Box 2)
  - Homoeothermic animals, undated (Box 2)
  - Hearing, undated (Box 2)
  - Hygiene, 1931, undated (Box 2)
  - Identifications, 1931-1932 (Box 2)
  - India, 1929-1932, undated (Box 2)
  - Insects and disease, undated (Box 2)
  - International Health Board, Rockefeller Foundation, 1925-1926 (Box 2)
  - Japan, 1928-1931 (Box 3)
  - Lasioderma, 1928-1929 (Box 3)
  - Lecture notes, undated (Box 3)
  - Light, undated (Box 3)
  - London:
    - 1930, undated (Box 3)
    - School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine, 1926 (Box 3)
    - British Army School of Hygiene [lecture and lab notes], 1926, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Maya, 1931-1937 (Box 3)
  - Maine, 1933-1934 (Box 3)
  - Methods, 1930, undated (Box 3)
  - Migration from Ocean, 1930, undated (Box 3)
  - Mind development, undated (Box 3)
  - Mind experiments, undated (Box 3)
  - Misaki, 1926-1929 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 1936-1958, undated (Box 3)
  - National Science Foundation:
    - Advisory Committee to Biological Science Division, 1952, undated (Box 3)
    - Biological and Medical Sciences Advisory Panel, 1952 Oct. 17, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Nervous system, 1932, undated (Box 3)
  - Notes-Abstracts, [ca. 1920s-40s], 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Notes on soil, 1937-1950 (Box 3)
  - Parasitology, 1933, 1938, undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Phylum, 1952 (Box 3)
  - Printed material and clippings, [ca. 1940s-1950s] (Box 3)
  - Problems, undated (Box 3)
  - Protozoa, undated (Box 3)
  - Research grant material, 1949-1953, undated (Box 3)
  - Research proposals, 1926, 1931, undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Salamanders, 1929-1931 (Box 3)
  - Sand beaches, 1929-1931 (Box 3)
  - Siam, 1929-1933 (Box 3)
  - Snails, 1951-1952 (Box 4)
  - Speeches and lectures, notes, 1927-1939 (Box 4)
  - Spatial temperature, undated (Box 4)
  - Stylochus inimicus, undated (Box 4)
  - Systematic, 1925 (Box 4)
  - Systematics (reading), undated (Box 4)
  - Tortugas, 1928, 1931-1933, undated, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Touch, undated (Box 4)
  - Turtles, 1914-1933 (Box 4)
  - Tropical medicine and parasitology, 1933 (Box 4)
  - The Tropics, 1929, undated (Box 4)
  - Vitae, undated (Box 4)
  - Vitalism, 1932, undated (Box 4)
  - Worm commensals, 1927 (Box 4)
  - Worms in F.W., 1927, undated (Box 4)
  - Zoological drawings and maps, undated (Box 4)
  - Zoological Journal Club, 1928-1934, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Zoology (lecture notes), 1914-1924 (Box 4)
- Graduate Students, 1917-1948
  This small series contains correspondence concerning graduate student research and thesis progress, plans of work, assigned reading lists, dissertation abstracts, and records of courses completed. Material is arranged alphabetically by student's name.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  In accordance with the federal government's Family Education Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA), Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records. Education records include those records which contain information directly related to a student and which are maintained as official working files by the University.
  - Altland-Young, 1917-1948, 4 folders (Box 4)
- Manuscripts, 1923-1952 and undated; 1.25 boxes
  Series contains manuscripts of essays, monographs, and textbooks written by Pearse during his professional career, including reprint editions of Animal Ecology and various working drafts of The Migration of Animals from Sea to Land. Also present is an undated manuscript of a textbook written by Pearse's colleague B. Cunningham.
  - Adventure, 1942, 1948 (Box 4)
  - Animal Ecology:
    - Text, 1950, 4 folders (Box 4)
    - Text, 1950, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Tables and bibliography, 1950 (Box 5)
    - Bibliography and figures, 1950 (Box 5)
  - Beaches, undated (Box 5)
  - Bimini, 1948 (Box 5)
  - Biota of the Reefs off the Carolinas, with Louis Williams, 1949 (Box 5)
  - Cunningham, B., textbook, undated (Box 5)
  - Ecology in the Twentieth Century, undated (Box 5)
  - Emigration of Animals from the Sea, undated (Box 5)
  - Migration of Animals:
    - Introduction, 1923-1929 (Box 5)
    - Routes, 1950-undated (Box 5)
    - Causes, undated (Box 5)
    - Changes, undated (Box 5)
    - Ends, undated (Box 5)
  - The Migrations of Animals from Sea to Land, [ca. 1950s] (Box 5)
  - The Migration of Animals from Sea to Land, [Chinese], 1937 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous writings, undated (Box 5)
  - Parasitic Crustaceans from Alligator Harbor, Florida, 1952 (Box 5)
  - Parasitic Crustacea from the Gulf of Mexico, 1951 (Box 5)
  - Some Observations on the Land Snails in the Duke Forest, undated (Box 5)
  - Stability, undated (Box 5)
- Course Material, 1905-1923 and undated; .25 boxes
  Series contains material relating to courses taught by Pearse and includes laboratory guides, exercises, and techniques; lecture notes and outlines; lists of manuals, supplies, equipment, and specimen dealers; field trip locations, itineraries, and notes; and ruminations on pedagogical theory with inclusive dates 1905-1923. Most of the material is undated, however, all of the material relates to courses at the University of Wisconsin-Madison where Pearse taught from 1912-1927.
  - Field trips, undated (Box 6)
  - Lab and lecture outlines:
    - Zoology 161, undated (Box 6)
    - Zoology 18a, undated (Box 6)
    - Zoology, 120, undated (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 6)
  - Printed material, 1905, undated (Box 6)
  - Teaching of Zoology (teacher's course), 1923 (Box 6)
- Lab and Field Notebooks, 1904-1952; .75 boxes
  Series contains field notebooks created by Pearse on research trips and in laboratory work with inclusive dates 1904-1952. Titles are taken from the originals.
  Beginning with his graduate work at Harvard University, the notebooks document the eclectic research interests, career, and travels of Pearse throughout his professional life. Content ranges widely, from notes and statistics on local flora, fauna, and animal life to notes on local peoples and culture. Arrangement is chronological.
  Complementing the notebook entries are the images in the Photographic Materials series, taken to document the travels and projects.
  - Laboratory work in Paleontology with Prof. R.T. Jackson, 1904 Oct.1-1905 Jan. 25 (Box 6)
  - Comparative Histology under Prof. G.H. Parker, 1904 Oct. 1-1905 3 Jan. (Box 6)
  - Studies on the Anatomy of Glossiphonia Stagnalis, [ca. 1904-1905] (Box 6)
  - Fiddler wasp's nest, 1912 July (Box 6)
  - Chaetopterus Commensal: Isopoda, 1914 (Box 6)
  - General field notebook, 1916-1919, 2 notebooks (Box 6)
  - Windota, etc., 1916 April-Sept. (Box 6)
  - Wingra, 1916 April-1917 March (Box 6)
  - Lakes on Oconomonuac and Fox Rivers, 1917 Aug.-Sept. (Box 6)
  - Lake Valencia, specimens, 1918 July-Aug. (Box 6)
  - Lake Valencia, 1918 July-Aug. (Box 6)
  - Tagging, 1919, 1922, 2 notebooks (Box 6)
  - Green Lake, 1919 (Box 6)
  - Lake Pepia, 1920 June 19-July 14 (Box 6)
  - Sturgeon Bay, Wisconsin, 1920 July 17-Aug. 5 (Box 6)
  - Lake Geneva, 1920 Aug. 7-Aug. 25 (Box 6)
  - Mandota, 1921 May 24-1922 Sept. 5 (Box 6)
  - Lagos, Nigeria, 1926 (Box 6)
  - Yaba Yellow Fever Laboratory, Lagos, Nigeria, 1926 (Box 6)
  - Duke Forest, 1927-1933 (Box 6)
  - Beaufort, 1928, 3 notebooks (Box 6)
  - Beaufort, fieldwork, 1928 (Box 6)
  - Japan, 1929 March-Sept. (Box 6)
  - Aburatsuko (Misaki), Japan, 1929 March-Sept. (Box 6)
  - Tortugas, 1928 July-Aug. (Box 6)
  - Reminders, 1930 (Box 6)
  - Foochow, 1930 April (Box 6)
  - Siam, 1930 May-June (Box 6)
  - India, 1930 June-Aug. (Box 6)
  - Tortugas, 1931 June-Aug., 2 notebooks (Box 6)
  - Avenido Joaquin Ancona, 1932, 2 notebooks (Box 6)
  - Beaufort, 1934 March-July (Box 6)
  - Maine, North Carolina, Florida, 1934 July 20-1935 Oct. 15 (Box 6)
  - Florida, 1935 Oct.-1936 April, 2 notebooks (Box 6)
  - Yucatán, 1936 June-Aug. (Box 6)
  - General, 1937 March 31-1942 Jan. 7 (Box 6)
  - Beaufort, 1938 June-Aug., 3 notebooks (Box 6)
  - Beaufort, Maine, Canada, 1938 June-Sept. (Box 6)
  - Beaufort (U.S. Bureau of Fisheries), 1939 June (Box 6)
  - Doswell S. Edwards, 1940 Aug. 15-1945 Aug. 25, 5 notebooks (Box 6)
  - Beaufort (U.S. Bureau of Fisheries), 1941 May 28-1941 Sept. 11, 2 notebooks (Box 6)
  - General, 1947-1948 (Box 6)
  - Duke Forest/Fort Aransas, TX, 1951 Feb. 6-Nov. 17 (Box 6)
  - Duke Forest, 1951 Nov. 23-1952 Nov. 25 (Box 6)
  - Alligator Harbor, FL, 1952 April-1952 June (Box 6)
  - Henrietta Achtenberg, undated (Box 6)
- Photographic Material, 1911-1953; 6 boxes
  Series contains over 1000 photographs and corresponding negatives, a few postcards, and glass lantern slides primarily documenting Pearse's research travels abroad and within the United States from 1911-1953. Locations with the most photographic images are Nigeria and the Yucatán Peninsula, with smaller numbers from the Duke Beaufort Marine Lab, the NC Outer Banks, Colombia, India, Japan, China, the Philippines, and Venezuela.
  Photographs of local flora, fauna, and ecosystems include: fish, crabs and other crustaceans, insects, and turtles; geological and ecological settings, particularly relating to freshwater and coastal zones; cenotes (large sinkholes and caves) in the Yucatán; and mixed zones of agriculture and tropical forest.
  Also present are many prints and negatives of charts, maps, animals, and other illustrations used in Pearse's texbooks.
  In addition to scientific research photographs, there are images, particularly those from Nigeria and the Yucatán, which document local peoples, customs, and activities, including dress, religious customs, agricultural techniques, food gathering, and architecture such as walled villages and temples.
  Single items of interest include a signed portrait of naturalist and Darwinist T.R.R. Stebbing, circa 1915, and a photograph of a group of men from the Association of American Universities taken by the Bayard Wooten-Moulton studio in Chapel Hill, N.C. sometime before 1954.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Negatives are closed to access; use copies exist in the form of photographic prints, though there are also negatives for which prints may not exist. Negatives are slated for digitization.
  Glass lantern slides are also closed to general use; scans may be made upon advance request.
  Please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use this collection.
  - Photographic prints, 1912-1953; 1 boxes; Approximately 367 prints
    Scope and Contents
    Titles of folders are taken from the original envelopes. Sizes range from 1.5 x 2.5 to 4 x 6 inches, with only a few larger prints. Almost all are early black-and-white gelatin silver prints printed from nitrate negatives. Includes a few postcards, including several showing the interiors of a Japanese medical school, circa 1929-1930.
    - Association of American Universities, group portrait, 1930s? (Box 7)
      Stamp on back: "Wooten-Moulton Photographers, Chapel Hill, NC" (sold in 1954)
    - Beaufort Marine Lab, 1938 (Box 7)
    - Blackbeard Island, N.C., circa 1930s (Box 7)
    - Burma, 1929-1930 (Box 7)
    - Colombia, 1913 (Box 7)
    - Duke Forest, 1934 (Box 7)
    - India, 1929-1930 (Box 7)
    - Japan: Kyoto Medical School postcards and flyer in Japanese, circa 1929 (Box 7)
    - Maps, charts, and illustrations, undated (Box 7)
    - Massachusetts, 1912-1913 (Box 7)
    - Nigeria, 1926, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Philippine Islands, circa 1929 (Box 7)
    - People, circa 1915, circa 1930, 1953 (Box 7)